Guide to the Ruth Ford Papers
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Ruth Ford papers
1940-1989
YCAL MSS 847
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.88
(6 boxes) + 1 broadside
Ford, Ruth, 1911-2009
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
The collection consists of correspondence with and topical and production files relating to plays of Edward Albee, Kenward Elmslie, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, James Purdy, Tennessee Williams, and others. Also included are scripts of works submitted to her for her review and/or plays and screenplays in which she acted including plays by Martin Crowley, Lawrence Ferlinghetti, and Tennessee Williams; stage and film production stills and candid and portrait photographs; and printed invitations to parties, openings, and other events at New York City nightclubs.
Arrangement
Arranged by type of material.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Acquired by purchase from various sources on multiple funds, 2010-2012. For more information consult the appropriate curator.
Ruth Ford (1911-2009)
Ruth Ford was born in Brookhaven, Mississippi in 1911. In the 1930s, after graduating from the University of Mississippi with bachelor's and master's degrees, she moved to New York City where she was introduced to writers, musicians, and other artists by her brother Charles Henri Ford, himself a poet and artist living in New York. Ruth Ford was photographed by Carl Van Vechten, Man Ray, and Cecil Beaton, and as a fashion model she appeared in magazines including Harper's Bazaar, Mademoiselle, and Vogue. She had a successful acting career, performing in stage productions including The Shoemaker's Holiday (1938), No Exit (1946), Requiem for a Nun (1959), and Harold and Maude (1980). As a film actress, she had roles in over two dozen films, including Secrets of the Lone Wolf (1941) and The Keys of the Kingdom (1944). On television she appeared in several productions of The United States Steel Hour (1954-1961) as well as numerous other series and made-for-television movies. She was well known for the modern-day salons that she held in her apartment in the Dakota apartment building where her guests included Truman Capote, Tennessee Williams, William Faulkner, Stephen Sondheim, Edward Albee, and many others. Her first marriage to Peter van Eyck ended in divorce. She married the actor Zachary Scott in 1952, and they were the parents of one daughter, Shelly Scott. Ruth Ford died in New York City in 2009.
Actresses -- United States; Models (Persons) -- United States; Motion picture actors and actresses -- United States; Motion pictures -- Production and direction -- United States; Television -- Production and direction -- United States; Television actors and actresses -- United States; Photographs -- United States -- 20th Century; Scripts (documents) -- United States -- 20th Century; Actresses -- United States -- 20th Century; Models (Persons) -- United States -- 20th Century; Albee, Edward, 1928-2016; Crowley, Martin; Elmslie, Kenward, 1929-; Ferlinghetti, Lawrence, 1919-; Ford, Ruth, 1911-2009; Purdy, James, 1914-2009; Williams, Tennessee, 1911-1983
- Correspondence, production, and topical files, 1940-1989
  - Albee, Edward
    - Correspondence, 1962-1988; 2 (Box 1)
    - Clippings, 1991, undated (Box 1)
  - Bowles, Paul
    - Adaptation of Sartre's No Exit; script, annotated; with program and clipping, 1950, undated (Box 1)
  - Crowley, Martin
    - Correspondence and clippings, 1969-1989, undated; 9 (Box 1)
    - "A Breeze from the Gulf" script, [circa 1973] (Box 1)
  - Curtis, Jackie
    - Correspondence and printed ephemera, 1969-1984 (Box 1)
  - Didion, Joan
    - Notes, production programs, clippings and printed ephemera regarding Play It As It Lays by Joan Didion and John Gregory Dunne, 1972 (Box 1)
    - "Play It As It Lays" filmscript, 1971 November 24 (Box 1)
  - Elmslie, Kenward
    - Correspondence, clippings, and printed ephemera, circa 1971-1979; 2 (Box 1)
    - Postcards, circa 1969-1980 (Box 1)
    - Plays
      - "The Grass Harp: A Musical Play," book and lyrics by Elmslie Kenward, music by Claibe Richardson, based on the novel by Truman Capote, scripts
        - Scripts, [1971?]; 3 (Box 1)
        - Production programs, heralds, and other ephemera, 1971-1977 (Box 1)
        - Clippings, 1971-1972 (Box 1)
        - "Songs from the Grass Harp," television adaptation, script, 1977 (Box 1)
  - Ferlinghetti, Lawrence
    - Correspondence with Ruth Ford, 1962 (Box 2)
    - Correspondence between Ruth Ford and James Laughlin and others regarding Ferlinghetti; with manuscript and typed notes by Ford, 1962-1964; 2 (Box 2)
    - Scripts
      - "The Alligation", 1962 (Box 2)
      - "Light Bulbs" (four copies), undated (Box 2)
      - "The Soldiers of No Country", 1962 (Box 2)
      - "Three Thousand Red Ants" (four copies), 1962 (Box 2)
  - James, Edward Frank Willis, handmade Valentine, undated (Box 2)
  - Jones, Leroi [Amiri Baraka], "The Slave" script, undated (Box 2)
  - Purdy, James
    - Correspondence, clippings and printed ephemera, 1961-1989; 2 (Box 2)
    - Scripts
      - "Band Music", 1984 (Box 2)
      - "Bright Summer Stars", [1986?] (Box 2)
      - "Children Is All", 1961 (Box 2)
      - "Malcolm"; with notes and printed ephemera, 1961 (Box 2)
      - "Souvenirs", 1984 (Box 2)
  - Walcott, Derek
    - "The Charlatan"
      - Correspondence, contract, clippings and printed ephemera, 1874 (Box 2)
      - Script (three versions), 1974, undated; 3 (Box 2)
  - Williams, Tennessee
    - Correspondence with Ruth Ford, 1945-1975 (Box 2)
    - Ruth Ford correspondence regarding Tennessee Williams, 1974-1985 (Box 2)
    - "Memoirs," typescript with annotations of various numbered pages, undated (Box 2)
    - Plays
      - "Creve Coeur" script (two versions), 1977-1978; 2 (Box 2)
      - "The Milk Train Doesn't Stop Here Anymore"
        - Contract, correspondence, production program, and other material, 1963-1971 (Box 2)
        - Script, 1963 (Box 2)
      - "A Streetcar Named Desire"
        - Contracts, telegrams, production programs and other printed ephemera, 1848-1949, undated (Box 2)
        - Script, 1947 December 3 (Box 2)
      - Suddenly Last Summer
        - Play published by New Directions, New York, 1958 (Box 3)
        - Script for reading at tribute to Williams, with event flyer, 1984 (Box 3)
    - "Which Sea-Gull at What Corner?" typescripts, corrected, and published article in issue of Esquire magazine, 1972; 3 (Box 3)
    - Production programs, clippings, and other printed material about Tennessee Williams (Box 3)
  - Invitations, 1979-1990
    Scope and Contents
    Includes printed cards, flyers, posters for parties, openings, and other events at nightclubs mainly in New York City.
    Arrangement
    Arranged by name of venue.
    - Area (Box 3)
    - Cat Club (Box 3)
    - Danceteria (Box 3)
    - Limelight (Box 3)
    - Mars (Box 3)
    - Max's Kansas City (Box 3)
    - New York, New York (Box 3)
    - Nirvana (Box 3)
    - Palladium, 2 (Box 3)
    - Private Eyes (Box 3)
    - Quick (Box 3)
    - Red Parrot (Box 3)
    - Red Zone (Box 3)
    - Ritz (Box 3)
    - Roxy (Box 3)
    - The Saint (Box 3)
    - Studio 54 (Box 3)
    - Tunnel (Box 3)
    - Underground (Box 3)
    - Visage (Box 3)
    - Xenon (Box 3)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 3)
- Photographs
  - Portrait photographs, 1941-1978; 4 (Box 4)
  - "Hollywood Portraits", 1941-1945; 2 (Box 4)
  - "[Photographs of Ford wearing] Hollywood clothes I designed for myself and more", circa 1940 (Box 4)
  - Ford with Dotson Rader, undated (Box 4)
  - Miscellaneous photographs of Ford, 1973, undated (Box 4)
  - Candid photographs of Ford and friends, circa1941-1973 (Box 4)
  - Film stills
    - Act One (1963); Born for Trouble [ Murder in the Big House ] (1942); Dragonwyck (1946), 1942-1963 (Box 4)
    - The Keys of the Kingdom, 1944 (Box 4)
    - Play It As It Lays, 1972 (Box 4)
    - Roaring Frontiers, 1941 (Box 4)
    - Secrets of the Lone Wolf, 1941 (Box 4)
    - Wilson, 1944 (Box 4)
  - Stage production photographs
    - American Dream, 1962 (Box 5)
    - The Aspern Papers, 1978 (Box 5)
    - The Charlatan, 1974 (Box 5)
    - The Children of Darkness, [1950?] (Box 5)
    - Clutterbuck, 1949 (Box 5)
    - The Grass Harp, 1971 (Box 5)
    - Hunger and Thirst, 1969 (Box 5)
    - Lovey, 1965 (Box 5)
    - Requiem for a Nun, 1959 (Box 5)
- Posters
  - Poster for poetry event in Vermont featuring Ruth Ford, undated
  - Window card for A Breeze from the Gulf, 1973 (Box 6 (Broadside))
- Oversize
  - Portrait photographs (Box 7 (Oversize))
  - "[Photographs of Ford wearing] Hollywood clothes I designed for myself and more" (Box 7 (Oversize))